Finding aid for the Exhibit Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts, 1492-1848 LSC.1656
UCLA Library Special Collections
Exhibit Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts
1492-1848
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.1656
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Collection consists of Persian, Ottoman Turkish, Arabic, and Armenian manuscripts dating from 1492-1848. The collection includes bound manuscripts, scrolls, manuscript fragments, decorative book covers, and artifacts. Subjects include history, lexicography, belles-lettres, theology, and philosophy.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
In 1991, for a potential future exhibition, the majority of the items in this collection were selected from two other collection in the department: the Minasian Collection og Near Eastern Manuscripts (Collection 1147) and the Qayani Collection of Arabic and Persian Manuscripts (Collection 1053).
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942329963606533
Scope and Content
The collection consists of illustrated and illuminated manuscripts from the ?afawid, Ottoman, Qajar, and Timurid domains, illustrated Armenian scrolls, decorative lacquered book covers, and several artifacts. There are eight works of belles-lettres, including two royal correspondence handbooks (one Persian, one Ottoman Turkish); four works of a religious nature, including two Koran fragments and a brilliantly illuminated Koran in a Qajar lacquered binding; four works of history, including manuscript versions of unedited texts; and single volumes of lexicography, logic, and philosophy. Of particular scholarly interest is a version of the ninth section of Kemalpasazade's Histories of the Ottoman House (Al-daftar al-tas? min al-dafatir al-marsuma bi al-Sulaymaniyya), and Mu?n al-Din Yazdi's Humayun nama, ya, Mavahib-i ilahi (Book of Humayun, or, Divine gifts). The collection includes numerous fine examples of Nast? liq script, one striking example of Divani calligraphy, and many beautiful leaves demonstrating ornate Qajar illumination, illustration, and decoration techniques. Artifacts include embroidered purses and a leather book bag.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Manuscripts
Scrolls
Book covers and artifacts
Related Material
Minasian Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts (Collection 1147). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Qayani Collection of Arabic and Persian Manuscripts (Collection 1053). Available in the Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Wellcome Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts (Collection 1148). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Persian and Arabic manuscripts in Special Collections Catalog Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Exhibit Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts (6 items).
manuscripts (documents) -- Arab countries.
- Manuscripts
  - Kanz al-lughat / Treasure of words, 1658; Manuscript no. 1; 375 leaves: paper, ill.; 212 × 120 (167 × 77) mm. bound to 217 × 124 mm. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Persian dictionary of Koranic Arabic and Hadith terms. The author praises Sul?an Mu?ammad and his heir (2a) and calls them "The adornment of the Hall of the Mus?afawi lineage, and the decoration of the pride of the Murta?awi family," implying a Sayyid king, possibly ?afawid. If so, the named Sul?an would be Sul?an Mu?ammad Khudabandah father of Shah ?bbas, and the date of composition would fall between 1577-1586 CE.
    Author: Mu?ammad ibn ?bd al-Khaliq ibn Ma 'arif, fl. 16th cent?
    Scribe: Ibn Abi Turab Mu?ammad Ibrahim (al-?usayn?)
    Language: Text in Persian and Arabic
    Origin: ?afawid Persia
    Layout: Average of 21 lines of text per page.
    Script: Written in fine nast? liq hand.
    Decoration: Illuminated title page.
    Binding: Decorated red leather binding. Covers painted with portraits of youths; inside covers painted with partridges.
    Additional description: Arabic terms and phrases in red. Marginalia. Occasional bleeding of red ink, particularly in the last third of the text; light brown staining and black ink stains on a number of leaves. Misspelled fore-edge title; spine title.
    Contents:
    ff. 1b-3a: Preface
    ff. 3a-4b: Table of contents
    ff. 4b-375a: Twenty eight chapters according to the letters of the alphabet (alif to ya).
  - Kalilah va Dimnah / Kalilah and Dimnah, 1787; Manuscript no. 2; 262 leaves: paper, ill.; 211 × 148 mm. bound to 211 × 148 mm. (Box 1)
    Belles-lettres, also known as Kalilah va Dimnah, ya, Anvar-i Suhayli (Kalilah and Dimnah, or, Lights of Canopus). Kashifi gives the history of the fables from the "Indian" version of Bidpay (3a), to Burziyah's Pahlavi (3a), Ibn al-Muqann? [sic] in Arabic (3b), Ridaki's Persian in verse (3b), and the prose Persian version of Bahram Shah Ghaznawid (3b). Kashifi states (4a) that the book was in danger of not being read on account of the difficulties in the language of the Bahram Shah version, which he (Kashifi) has now undertaken to make more accessible to his contemporaries (4a-5b). This was suggested to him by (4b) Amir Shaykh A?mad, known as al-Suhayli (d. 1501-3 CE), hence the second title of the book and the pun on Suhayl, or the star Canopus. The work was done at the time of the Timurid Sultan ?usayn Bayqara (4b), who reigned in Heart until 1506 CE.
    Author: Kashifi, ?usayn Va ?i?, d. 1504 or 5
    Language: Text in Persian
    Origin: Persia
    Binding: Black laquered book cover with floral ornamentation.
    Additional description: Punctuation and introductory words in red ink. Marginalia in two hands: one hand resembles the scribe's, the other seems to have been involved in the production of the book (i.e. on leaf 227a, the second hand has extended the gilt text box to accommodate notes). Leaves 3 and 4 are detached, and 88 is missing. The copier has dated the finishing of some of the chapters.
    ff. 1b-6a: Kashifi's preface
    ff. 6a-29b: Introduction
    ff. 29b-78b: Chapter one: on avoiding to listen to the words of a slanderer and calumniator
    ff. 78b-104a: Chapter two: on evil-doers finding their recompense and the inauspiciousness of their end
    ff. 104a-126b: Chapter three: on the benefits of being in harmony with friends and supporting them
    ff. 126b-157a: Chapter four: on keeping an eye on enemies and not feeling secure
    ff. 157a-169b: Chapter five: on the harmfulness of negligence and losing what is sought
    ff. 169b-175a: Chapter six: on the curse of haste and the harm of precipitancy
    ff. 175a-185a: Chapter seven: on prudence and discretion and finding deliverance from the snare of adversaries by ruses
    ff. 185a-194a: Chapter eight: on being on one's guard against men of malice and not relying upon their flattery
    ff. 194a-210a: Chapter nine: on the merit of forgiveness and discretion which are the best adjuncts to kings
    ff. 210a-216b: Chapter ten: on the recompense of deeds in the manner of punishments
    ff. 216b-223b: Chapter eleven: on the harmfulness of desiring too much at the expense of doing one's task
    ff. 223b-240a: Chapter twelve: on the merit of self-possession and dignity and being settled and staid, particularly for kings
    ff. 240a-250a: Chapter thirteen: on avoiding the words of men of treachery and treason
    ff. 250a-262a: Chapter twelve: on not regarding the fluctuations of time and basing One's affairs on fate and divine decree.
  - Yisuf va Zulaykha / Yusuf and Zulaikha, 1511; Manuscript no. 3; 152 leaves: paper; 222 × 120 mm. bound to 206 × 123 mm. (Box 1)
    Belles-lettres. Jami's allegorical romance, in verse (completed 1483 CE).
    Author: Jami, 1414-1492
    Scribe: ?la al-Din Mu?ammad al-Haravi
    Origin: Timurid Herat
    Layout: Average of 14 lines of text in two columns per page.
    Script: Written in a nasta? liq hand.
    Decoration: Illumination on title page.
    Binding: Black leather binding with stamped gilt leather decoration; painted red endpapers.
    Additional description: Verses enclosed in gold and blue text box. Episode headings generally one to three lines; first line blue, second line gold, and third line red. Pagination in ink on upper corners.
    ff. 1b-18a: Opening verses
    ff. 18a-19a: The story of the lighting of the candle of Yisuf's beauty in the otherworldly night-chamber and the burning of Adam's heart upon witnessing that light
    ff. 19a-21b: How the sapling of Yisuf's beauty was brought into the Garden of Testimony, and how it was nourished by the tears of Jacob's eyes and the desires of Zulaykha's heart
    ff. 21b-24b: On the qualities and attributes of Zulaykha, from the sunrise of whose beauty, the occident had become the orient, but even a thousand degrees more so
    ff. 24b-26a: On how Zulaykha saw in the scabbard of sleep the sword of Yisuf's beauty for the first time, and how she was love-slain by that sword in the scabbard
    ff. 26a-27b: On how the morning breeze blew upon Zulaykha and awakened her sleepy narcissus eyes, and on how she drank the blood of her heart like a blossom and sealed her lips from the nightly vision
    ff. 27b-30b: On how the string of the intellect of maidens was tied into a knot of astonishment when they witnessed the change in Zulaykha's condition, and how her nurse untied that knot by the fingertips of interrogation
    ff. 30b-33b: How Zulaykha saw Yisuf in a dream a second time, and how the chains of her love quavered, dragging her into the embroilment of madness
    ff. 33b-35b: On how Yisuf came to her dream a third time, and how she learned his name and status, returning to sanity and consciousness
    ff. 35b-37b: How the envoys of the monarchs of those parts other than Egypt came to ask for Zulaykha's hand, and how her heart was constricted from her resulting despair
    ff. 37b-39b: How Zulaykha's father sent a messenger to the ?ziz of Egypt, offering her to him, and how he accepted it
    ff. 39b-41b: How the breeze of acceptance blew from Egypt, and how Zulaykha's litter was conveyed to Egypt like a bouquet of flowers
    ff. 41b-43a: How the ?ziz of Egypt found out that Zulaykha had arrived, and how he rose to set out for her welcoming, and how he adorned the army of Egypt in rich array
    ff. 43a-45a: How Zulaykha saw the ?ziz of Egypt from an opening in the pavilion-tent and cried "He is not the one I have seen in my dream, and for whom I have suffered the tribulations of love"
    ff. 45a-47a: How Zulaykha came into Egypt along with the ?ziz of Egypt, and how the Egyptians came out and sprinkled trayfuls of offerings upon Zulaykha's litter
    ff. 47a-50a: How Zulaykha spent her days in the absence of Yisuf, and how she pined and grieved during the passing of those mornings and nights
    ff. 50a-51a: The beginning of the brothers' jealousy, and how they cast Yisuf out of Canaan
    ff. 51a-52b: How Yisuf dreamed that the sun and the moon and twelve stars were bowing down to him, and how the brothers heard this, and how their jealousy was increased
    ff. 52b-53b: How the brothers held council with one another to see what ruse they might devise to separate Yisuf from their father
    ff. 53b-54b: How the brothers went to their father and asked him to take Yisuf into the wilderness with them
    ff. 54b-57a: How the brothers took Yisuf away from their father, and how they dug a well of darkness in the path of their own guidance, throwing him who was guiltless into the well
    ff. 57a-59a: How the caravan arrived at the well, and how they took Yisuf out of the well, illuminating the world once again by the light of his beauty
    ff. 59a-60a: How the proprietor brought Yisuf to the environs of Egypt, and how the king found out about it and sent the ?ziz to their welcoming
    ff. 60a-61b: How Yisuf got into the river Nile to wash himself of the dust of the road, and how he sat in a litter intending for the court of the king of Egypt
    ff. 61b-63a: How Zulaykha, arriving at court and asking the reason for the congestion, saw Yisuf's beauty and recognized him
    ff. 63a-65a: How the proprietor presented Yisuf for sale, and how Zulaykha bought him by doubling what the others were buying him for
    ff. 65a-68a: The story of a girl named Bazigha, a descendant of the ?id, who was like none other in her wealth and beauty, and who fell in love with Yisuf absently, and saw the Truth in that mirror of beauty, and reached the Truth via that path
    ff. 68a-70a: How Zulaykha instructed Yisuf, and how she served him with whatever was at hand
    ff. 70a-71b: How Yisuf described the tribulations of the road and the agonies of the well, and how Zulaykha realized that this was the cause for his sadness that day
    ff. 71b-72b: How Yisuf besought a shepherd, on account of the fact that there has never been a prophet who did not herd livestock, and how Zulaykha prepared the means of his shepherding
    ff. 72b-74a: How Zulaykha asked Yisuf for attainment, and how Yisuf fled from her
    ff. 74a-75b: How the nurse asked Zulaykha the cause of her burning and smoldering
    ff. 75b-77a: How Zulaykha sent the nurse to Yisuf to ask for her wish, and …[text faded]
    ff. 77a-79b: How Zulaykha went herself to Yisuf and implored, and how Yisuf excused himself from satisfying her desire
    ff. 79b-81b: How Zulaykha sent Yisuf to the garden and how she set him up
    ff. 81b-83b: How evening fell, and how the maidens presented their beauties to Yisuf, to see unto which one of them would Yisuf be inclined
    ff. 83b-85a: How Zulaykha implored her nurse for a ruse that would bring about the attainment of Yisuf
    ff. 85a-86b: How the nurse built a house in which the pictures of Yisuf and Zulaykha were painted
    ff. 86b-90a: How Zulaykha summoned Yisuf into that house and asked for attainment
    ff. 90a-95a: How Zulaykha brought Yisuf into the seventh house, and how she set forth her endeavor into the Nile of desire, and how Yisuf ran away and left her rueful and pining
    ff. 95a-97b: How the ?ziz of Egypt came up to Yisuf in front of that house, and how [Yisuf] hid what had past between him and Zulaykha, and how Zulaykha divulged it
    ff. 97b-99a: How the captains dragged Yisuf to prison, and how a nursling infant testified to his innocence, and how he was left alone
    ff. 99a-103a: How the women of Egypt removed their hands from the mouths, and began upbraiding Zulaykha, and how the sword of the zeal of love cut their tongues and hands
    ff. 103a-105b: How the women of Egypt excused Zulaykha after they had witnessed Yisuf's beauty, and how Yisuf disdained submission to Zulaykha, and how she threatened him with imprisonment
    ff. 105b-108a: How the women of Egypt induced Zulaykha to send Yisuf to prison, and how Zulaykha obeyed them
    ff. 108a-111a: How Zulaykha regretted having sent Yisuf to prison, and how she began to weep and wail for his absence
    ff. 111a-113b: How Zulaykha grew impatient at Yisuf's absence, and how she went to prison at night along with the nurse and witnessed his beauty
    ff. 113b-115b: How in daytime Zulaykha went to the rooftop of her palace, and watched the rooftop of the prison from there, and how she began weeping and moaning over his absence
    ff. 115b-117a: The description of how Yisuf did good to the men in jail, and how he interpreted the dream of the confidants of the king of Egypt, and how he charged one of them to recall him to the king
    ff. 117a-120a: How the king of Egypt requested Yisuf for the interpreting of his dream, and how he pleaded that he investigate into what had passed between him and the women of Egypt
    ff. 120a-122a: How Yisuf came out of prison, and how the king honored him, and how the ?ziz of Egypt passed away, and how Zulaykha was stricken with loneliness and separation
    ff. 122a-125a: The description of Zulaykha's condition after the death of the ?ziz of Egypt, and how the love of Yisuf overpowered her, and how she was stricken with the tribulation of estrangement
    ff. 125a-127a: How Zulaykha came to Yisuf's way and built a hovel so she might find solace at the sound of the passing of his army
    ff. 127a-129a: How Zulaykha blocked Yisuf's way, and how she did not find favor, and how afterwards she went home, broke the idol, believed in God most high, went back to his way, and found favor
    ff. 129a-131b: How Zulaykha came to the private house of Yisuf, and how, by his prayers, she regained her sight, beauty, and youth
    ff. 131b-133b: How Yisuf took Zulaykha as wife by the order of God most high, and how he took her to the marriage bed
    ff. 133b-135b: How the love for Zulaykha overpowered Yisuf, and how he built a house of worship for her
    ff. 135b-137a: How Yisuf saw his mother and father in a dream, and how he asked God most high to pass away, and how Zulaykha panicked
    ff. 137a-142a: How Yisuf passed away, and how Zulaykha died from the pain of his separation
    ff. 142a-152a: closing material.
  - Ma?l?-i s?dayn va majm? -i ba?rayn / The rising of the auspicious [lunar] mansions, and the gathering of the seas, 1492; Manuscript no. 4; 430 leaves: paper, ill.; 251 × 163 mm. bound to 253 × 167 mm. (Box 1)
    History. This is the second volume of Samarqandi's history of the Ilkhanid Mongols, Tamerlane, and the Timurids. Volume two covers the sons of Tamerlane up to ca. 1469 CE; also including the enthronement of Sul?an ?usayn Bayqara, ca. 1470 CE. While the first volume of this book borrowed from several other histories, the second volume reported the events that were contemporary, or near contemporary, with the author. The focus is mostly on events in Khurasan and Transoxiana, with due attention given to events in Iraq and Azerbayjan. The reign of the following Timurid Emirs are covered with varying degree of detail: Pir Mu?ammad, Rustam, Khalil Sul?an, ?Umar Shaykh, Shah Rukh, Ulugh Beg, ?bd al-La?if, ?bd Allah, Abi S? id, Sul?an A?mad, Ma?mid, and ?usayn Bayqara. The book also contains the report of the author's travels to India as an ambassador and his account of the strange things that he had seen there. The author refers to himself and his date of composition in a number of other instances, for example 58a (at the end of the section on Shahrukh's school and hospice built in Heart ca. 1410), or when he mentions his interview with Shahrukh ca. 1437 (192b).
    Author: ?bd al-Razzaq Kamal al-Din ibn Is?aq al-Samarqandi, 1413-1482
    Scribe: ?bd al-Mi'min ibn Maq?id ?li al-Mu?allim
    Origin: [Northeast Persia or Afghanistan?]
    Binding: Red leather binding with gilt stamping.
    Additional description: Chapter headings, Koranic verses, and the words "verse" or "poem" in red ink. Each leaf has been numbered on the "b" side, in the right margin. Occasional streaking of ink, and ink-stained fingerprints. Possible water damage at tail.
    ff. 1a-3b: Opening
    ff. 3b-11b: The enthronement of Shah Rukh Mirza
    ff. 11b-31a: Events of 808-809 AH
    ff. 31a-100a: Events of 810-819 AH
    ff. 100a-156b: Events of 820-829 AH
    ff. 156b-188b: Events of 830-849 AH
    ff. 188b-235a: Events of 840-849 AH
    ff. 235a-314a: Events of 850-859 AH
    ff. 314a-387b: Events of 860-869 AH
    ff. 387b-430a: Events of 870-874 AH.
  - Tarassul / Letter writing, 1604; Manuscript no. 5; 67 leaves: paper; 215 × 135 mm. bound to 217 × 140 mm. (Box 1)
    Correspondence manual. This is a handbook of official correspondence, meant for secretaries, providing samples of letters to various government functionaries or potentates according to rank or the occasion. These include not only letters addressed to Sultans (3b), letters to Sultans on occasion of victories (4b), letters addressed to supreme Emirs (9b), viziers (11b), judges (16b), etc.; but also how to answer such letters.
    Author: Manṣῡr ibn Muḥammad ibn ̒Alῑ al-Qazvῑnῑ
    Origin: [?afawid Persia?]
    Layout: Average of 8 lines of text per page.
    Script: Divani.
    Binding: Black leather binding with blind stamping.
    Additional description: Blue paper with ivory and pink paper inlays. Headings and some punctuation in red ink. Pagination in Arabic numerals stamped on top right and left hand of facing pages. Fore-edge title.
    ff. 1a-1b: Blank
    ff. 2a: Date
    ff. 2b-3b: Opening
    ff. 3b-66b: Sample letters
    ff. 67a-67b: Blank.
  - Asas al-iqtibas / The foundations of learning, Manuscript no. 6; 276 leaves: paper; 181 × 120 mm. bound to 184 × 120 mm. (Box 1)
    Philosophy and logic. The division of the manuscript follows Aristotle's six-part "Logic," with the two appended books of "Rhetoric" and "Poetics," plus the additions of Porphyry of Tyre. Incomplete; page 1a begins in the middle of a sentence, and the critical edition of the text, ed. Mudarris Ra?awi (Tehran, 1976) shows this as the fourth line of the introduction.
    Author: ?usi, Na?ir al-Din Mu?ammad ibn Mu?ammad, 1201-1274
    Layout: Average of 19 lines of text per page.
    Script: Nast? liq.
    Binding: Burgundy leather binding with blind stamped leather inlays. Front cover has been replaced with blue cloth over a wooden board.
    Additional description: Chapter headings in red ink. Fairly extensive marginalia. Tables and charts (leaves 57-58). Spine title: Asas al-eqbas.
    ff. 1a-2a: Preface
    ff. 2a-13b: The First discourse: introduction to logic or Isagoge
    ff. 13b-24a: The Second discourse: on the ten classifications. It is called Categories
    ff. 24a-74a: The Third discourse: on interpretation. The target of these subjects is definitive statements. It is called Hermeneutics
    ff. 74a-147a: The Fourth discourse: on the science of analogies. It is called Prior Analytics
    ff. 147a-196a: The Fifth discourse: on proof. It is called Posterior Analytics
    ff. 196a-233b: The Sixth discourse: on argumentation. It is called Topics
    ff. 233b-240b: The Seventh discourse: on fallacies. It is called Sophistry
    ff. 240b-269a: The Eighth discourse: on oratory. It is called Rhetoric
    ff. 269a-276a: The Ninth discourse: on poetry. It is called Poetics.
  - Tu?fat al-mulik / The kings' gift, 1822; Manuscript no. 7; 201 leaves: paper, ill.; 288 × 191 mm. bound to 292 × 200 mm. (Box 2)
    Philosophy and belles-lettres. Political treatise written during the reign of Fat? ?li Shah Qajar at his request and that of the crown prince Mu?ammad ?aqi Mirza. The illustrations depict the circles of reason (often represented by the color of gold), and the circles of ignorance (often represented by black) to which people might ascend or descend.
    Author: Kashfi, Ja ?far ibn Abi Is?aq, d. 1850 or 51
    Scribe: Qasim ibn Mu?ammad al-Na?rabadi
    Origin: Qajar Persia
    Layout: Average of 29 lines of text per page.
    Decoration: Several large cosmological illustrations.
    Binding: Lacquered painted boards; outside covers show a floral medallion on a black background, bordered in gold; inside covers show a yellow flowering plant on an orange background.
    Additional description: Chapter and section headings in red ink. The leaves are frayed and have been poorly taped. Charts and illustrations throughout. Interlinear Persian and Arabic text from ff. 194- 198.
    ff. 1b-2b: Preface
    ff. 2b-18a: The first stratum: on the truth of reason
    ff. 18a-75b: The second stratum: on the quality of relationship, and its belonging to living beings, and all that belongs to it
    ff. 75b-137b: The third stratum: on the attributes and the signs and vestiges thereof, and that which belongs to them
    ff. 137b-187a: The closing: on one bit of the authority of reason which belongs to managing the populace; first part
    ff. 187a-201a: Second part.